Welcome to the very first lesson on the
PMP course.
1.1 projects.
Before we start examining the PINBOC
guide, we need to stop and consider some
basic concepts to make sure that we are
all on the same playing field.
So in this first lesson we will consider
what is not a project
and what is a project.
So number one, what is not a project?
Organizations need to do things every day
in order to remain in business.
These daily operations
tend to be repetitive and
really don't take much
in the way of planning.
Organizations usually have admission
statement which you should be able to find
on their website and
often if you visit their office
you'll find one in a frame
hanging on the wall somewhere.
Abmission statement says why the
organization exists.
and what it does.
For example, the Grey Campus mission
statement is Gray Campus transforms
careers through skills and certification
training.
We are a leading provider of training for
working professionals in the areas of
project management,
big data, data science,
service management and quality management.
We offer live online, instructor led
online, classroom, instructor-led
classroom, and e-learning, online
self-learning courses.
Our growing suite of accredited courses is
constantly upgraded to address the career
enhancement goals of working
professionals.
And this is what Gray Campus does every
day.
We call this everyday
work operations or business
as usual, which is often
abbreviated to BAU.
If a student wants to start
a new course, the great
campus staff follow a few
step-by-step instructions.
In fact, it's so simple and repetitive
that almost all is totally automated.
There's no need to involve senior
management or a project manager or hold
management meetings, develop a risk
management plan for a student starting a
new course or anything out of the
ordinary.
So then clearly operations are not
projects.
Operations maintain the organisation's
mission statement or to say another way,
operations maintain the organisation's
business as usual.
Two, what is a project?
To understand what a project is,
we will consider grey campus again working
every day to maintain its business as
usual.
But then something happens that is out of
the ordinary.
For example, there could be a change to
the country's tax laws.
PMI might release a new edition of the
PIMBOC guide and Great Campus may want a
new course developed for it, very like
this one.
They might decide to build a bricks and
mortar college somewhere.
They may decide to redesign their website
or redesign their office IT systems or get
a new e-learning platform or
countless other circumstances
that cannot be dealt with by
business as usual and that's key.
And so one of the clues that these might
be projects are each of these
circumstances requires
a significant change
but business as usual
does not involve change.
Now let's have a look at projects in more
detail.
The Pinball Guide defines projects as and
please note that many of these definitions
are critical for the
examination and obviously
project management
etc are critical definitions.
A project is a temporary endeavour
undertaken to create a unique product,
service or result.
Let's examine this definition a piece at a
time.
A project is a temporary endeavour.
The Oxford Dictionary defines temporary as
lasting for only a limited period of time,
not permanent.
And so right away we can see the contrast
with operational work.
A project lasts for only a limited period
of time, or to put it another way,
a project is planned to have a start at an
end date right from the beginning.
Operational work also has a start,
but at the start, there's no specific end
date planned, because in
reality, operational work will
continue until it is no longer
serving a useful purpose.
It is possible for a very large project to
last longer than some operations,
but the key point is that the project is
intended to be temporary and will
terminate when the products, services or
results that it was designed to deliver
have been completed and accepted by the
customer.
Note that it says temporary endeavour,
which means it is the endeavour,
the project, is temporary rather than the
product.
being temporary.
Think of Australia's famous Sydney Harbour
Bridge, for example.
The project lasted eight years, but
the product has lasted 85 years so far.
The second part of the definition is to
create a unique product, service or result.
The word unique is a little harder to
explain.
To be honest, I disagree with the
definition a bit.
I think it should actually be to uniquely
create a product, service or result
because the product itself is not
necessarily unique, it is the way the
product is created that is unique, which
means it is the project that is unique.
But anyway, to create a unique product,
service or result, as I said earlier,
operations are not
projects, but operations
require a project to
initially create them.
And to confuse matters a
little, some projects can be
similar to operations
for part of their life cycle.
For example, suppose you're planning a
project to lay a water pipeline to the
Sahara Desert from the source of water in
Martins in Mongolia 8,000 kilometers away.
This is clearly a project.
But for several years it would look very
like a process.
It should leave one piece of pipe,
next piece of pipe, next piece of pipe,
and so on.
However, the first key difference is that
the pipeline would have a planned,
start and end it.
And the second main difference
would be that permissions
would need to be sought
from various governments.
Different types of terrain would present
different challenges, rocky ground,
very soft ground and so on.
and so it still requires risk management,
quality management, schedule management,
cost management, resource management,
and so on.
And it would of course require project
manager to control the project.
How do we know what a project is finished?
Now that's an interesting point because
some of the projects that I've been
associated with seem to just go on forever
and ever and ever end.
The end of the project is
reached when at least one
of the following statements
about the project is true.
At a list like this, it's a possible
source for a question in the examination.
So how do we know the project has ended?
Okay, so at least one of the following is
true.
The project's objectives have been
achieved.
Number two, the objectives will not or
cannot be met.
If we can't meet them, there's no point in
the project.
keeping the project open, wasting time and
resources, close the project.
Funding is exhausted or no longer
available for allocation to the project,
so basically you've run out of money,
you can't afford to finish it.
The need for the project no longer exists.
For example, the customer no longer wants
the project completed, a change in
strategy or priority ends
the project, the organizational
management provides
direction to end the project.
For example, you've been working for the
last 120 years on the best steam engine
ever, but management decides we don't
think there's going to be a huge market in
the future for steam engines, let's just
end this project.
Next one is the human or physical
resources are no longer available.
Suppose you're doing a particular
project and you have specific
Highly trained resources and
they have quit the company.
You've looked around, you can't find
replacements in a reasonable length of time.
It is no option but just to close your
project.
Or the project is termed it for legal
cause or convenience.
Your company may be wind
up or one of the contractees
to your project by
taking legal action, etc.
Fulfilment of project
objectives may produce
one or more of the following deliverables.
A unique product that could be either a
component of another item, an enhancement
or correction to an item or an item in
itself.
For example, when you're developing a new
aircraft, a project might be undertaken to
deliver just the scope statement for the
aircraft project.
A unique service or capability to perform
a service.
For example, a project organisation may
wish to develop a training department.
A unique result, such as an outcome or
document.
Or, for example, a river flowing through a
major city has reached a non-acceptable
level of pollution and a
project is initiated to reduce
the pollution by 80% so
that, produces a unique result.
A unique combination of one or more
products, services or results,
for example new training course and
examination and a related mentoring service.
Repetitive elements may be present in some
project deliverables and activities,
as I mentioned before, a pipeline from
Mongolia to the Sahara Desert.
This repetition does not
change the fundamental
and unique characteristics
of the project work.
Another example would be office buildings
can be constructed with the same or
similar materials and maybe the same or
different teams.
However, each building remains unique in
key characteristics.
Example, location, design, environment,
location, I said location, location,
location, that's what they always say for
buildings anyway.
So, location, design, environment,
situation and people involved.
How many people are required for a
project?
There's actually no minimum or maximum
number.
A project can involve just one person or
thousands of people.
It can involve one group in an organisation
or many groups or many organisations.
It can exist within a single small
location such as, well, the initial
projects for the Apple Corporation which
began in the garage of a house,
or can span many countries like modern
Apple projects, as long as the endeavor is
intended to be temporary in nature and
will create at least one unique product,
service or result.
It is a project.
The Pinball Guide lists examples of
projects on page 5.
Projects drive change.
Processes just maintain business as usual,
They support the mission of the company,
but for the business
to remain competitive,
it has to occasionally
change its operations.
It might need to add new products or
services, improve the efficiency of its
current operations and so on, and so
projects are required, because changes
cannot be performed under a business as
usual.
In fact, project management has often been
called the management of change.
Projects in the business value creation.
PMI defines business
value as a net quantifiable
benefit derived from a business endeavor.
The benefit may be tangible, intangible or
both.
In business analysis, business value is
considered the return in the form of
elements such as time, money, goods, or
intangibles in return for
something exchanged.
Business value in projects
refers to the benefit that the
results of a specific project
provides to its stakeholders.
The benefit from projects may be tangible,
intangible or both.
Examples of tangible elements include
monetary assets, stakeholder equity,
utility, fixtures, tools and market share.
Examples of intangible elements include
goodwill, brand recognition, public
benefit, trademarks, strategic alignment
and reputation.
Project initiation context.
Organizational leaders initiate
projection response to four
fundamental categories of factors
acting upon their organisations.
As you can see in figure 1.2.
The four categories are meet regulatory,
legal or social requirements.
Satisfies to a order requests or needs,
implement or change business or
technological strategies
and create improved
or fixed products, processes or services.
These factors influence in organisations
ongoing operations in business strategy.
Leaders respond to these factors in order
to keep the organisation viable.
Projects provide the means for
organisations to successfully make the
changes necessary to deal with these
factors.
These factors ultimately should link to
the strategic objectives of the
organisation and the business value of
each project.
And finally, please study Table 1-1 on
page 9 of the PIMBalk Guide.
It would take much too long to discuss it
here and you'll find it's very easy to
understand and it shows
how factors could be aligned
with what or more of the
fundamental factor categories.
Now it brings us to the end of our first
lesson, 1.1 projects.
Please remember to learn the definition of
a project for the exam.
The next lesson is 1.2, the importance of
project management.
Please read the corresponding chapter of
the PIMBock Guide
before watching the video.